## Miguel Xochicale

## Curriculum Vitae – September 2020

#### Personal Details & Contact

Full name Miguel Angel Pérez Xochicale Date of birth 29-09-1981 Citizenship Mexican □ (+44) 0744 281 7616 (UK) Email miguel.xochicale@kcl.ac.uk

↑ http://mxochicale.github.io

**y** @ mxochicale

• @mxochicale

**ORCID:** 0000-0002-8225-7517

### Personal statement

I have passion for Robotics, Chaos, AI, Brains and Open Science. I am currently pushing forward the state-of-the-art of ultrasound-guided procedures by making scientific contributions to new algorithms, software and hardware. I have 21 years' experience in human-robot interaction, electronics, mechatronics and signal processing, along with 13 years' experience as a teaching assistant in Mechatronic and Computer Engineering.

#### Education

11/2014 - 11/2018 Ph.D. in Computer Engineering, University of Birmingham, UK.

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction. Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Thesis submission: 26/10/2018. Passed Viva: 11/01/2019. Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019. I published the first Open Access and 100% reproducible PhD Thesis since the establishment of University of Birmingham in 1900. Thesis: 🖾 Github: 🖶 Website: 🗹

09/2004 - 09/2006

M.Sc. in Signal Processing, Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics, México.

Thesis: Digital Filter FIR with less multipliers 🗷 🖶

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

08/1999 - 09/2004

**B.Eng.** in Electronics, Puebla Institute of Technology, México.

Thesis: Speed control for a two-degrees-of-freedom Robot in LabVIEW. 🖾 🐱

Supervisor: M.Sc. José Esteban Torres León.

### Professional Experience

04/2019 - present

Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering, King's College London.

Achievements: In the context of Ultrasound Needle Tracking, I am developing validation experiments with linear stages under Windows and GNU/Linux OS, designing electronic PCBs, characterising ultrasonic transducers, and contributing to real-time tracking software based on Python language via GitHub. All the previous activities in collaboration with an amazing team of renowned clinicians, engineers and researchers in KCL and UCL. Additionally, I am leading the preparation of two manuscripts.

02/2013 - 08/2013

Research Assistant in Robotics, INAOE's Robotics Laboratory, México.

Achievements: I developed a Human-Robot Interaction Demo for dancing activities based on a Patrolbot mobile robot and a ZSTAR3 Radio Frequency single three-axial accelerometer. (Documents and code:  $\square$ .

01/2012 - 01/2013

Lecturer in Mechatronic Engineering, Universidad Madero, Puebla, México.

Achievements: I proposed and supervised the following students' projects: Haptic Referee Glove, Lightmetre and Pychometre Sensors, Smart Irrigation, Persistent Of Vision Bicycle Wheel and a Delta Robot Structure (see documentation and code: 🗷). Additionally, I proposed and designed a Mechatronic Laboratory which includes: (i) a benchmark for laboratories in mechatronics in México and Puebla, (ii) a 3D layout design and (iii) minimal requirements of hardware and software for the laboratory (see documentation and layout:  $\square$ ).

09/2003 – 03/2004 Research Internship in Robotics, INAOE, México.

Achievements: I implemented a speed control for a two-degree-of-freedom robot with microcontrollers PIC 16F84 and 16F877 that made communication via RS-232 using Virtual Instruments on LabVIEW.

# Open Access Publications (OA). [ORCID ID: 0000-0002-8225-7517

#### Peer-Reviewed

[OA] Xochicale M and Baber C. Towards the Analysis of Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Imitation Activities. Bielefeld, Germany, October 2017. The 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI2017) 🔁 🖾 😸.

[OA] Xochicale M, Baber C, and Oussalah M. Analysis of the Movement Variability in Dance Activities using Wearable Sensors. Segovia, Spain, October 2016. The 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob16) 🖺 🖾 👼.

[OA] Xochicale M, Baber C, and Oussalah M. Understanding Movement Variability of Simplistic Gestures Using an Inertial Sensor. Oulu, Finland, June 2016. The 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays 🔁 🖾 🐱.

[OA] Xochicale M, Baber C, and Oussalah M. Towards the Quantification of Human-Robot Imitation Using Wearable Inertial Sensors. Vienna, Austria, March 2017. The 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI2017) 🖺 🖾 🐱.

#### **Preprints**

[OA] Xochicale M and Baber C. Strengths and weaknesses of Recurrence Quantification Analysis in the context of human-humanoid interaction. October 2018. ArXiv e-prints 🖺 🗹.

#### Non-Peer Reviewed

[OA] Xochicale M. Quantification of Dynamic Facial Expressions with Shannon Entropy in Human-Humanoid Interaction. London, UK, February 2019. 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS2019) 🔁 🖾 😸.

[OA] Xochicale M. Quantifying Movement Variability with Nonlinear Dynamics for Human-Humanoid Interaction. London, UK, June 2019. 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA2019) 🔁 🖾 😸.

[OA] Xochicale M. open-corTeX: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication. Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep 2020. 1st Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS20) 🔁 🖾 👼.

[OA] Xochicale M and Baber C. Quantifying the Inherent Chaos of Human Movement Variability. Madrid, Spain, June 2018. 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC15) 🔁 🗃 👼.

[OA] Xochicale M and Baber C. Towards the Analysis of Movement Variability for Facial Expressions with Nonlinear Dynamics. Glasgow, Scotland, UK, April 2018. The 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE2018) 🔁 🐱 😸.

## Teaching Experience

01/2020–04/2020 **Teaching Associate**, King's College London, UK. (01/2020-04/2020) Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Christos Bergeles

08/2014-04/2018 Teaching Associate, University of Birmingham, UK.

(01/2018-04/2018) Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Professor Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony

(08/2017–12/2017) Engineering Maths 2. Lecturer: Professor Martin Russell

(08/2017–12/2017) Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu

(01/2017-04/2017) Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte

(08/2016–12/2016) Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu

(08/2014–12/2014) Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Professor Chris Baber

08/2013–12/2013 **Teaching Associate**, Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University, Puebla, México. Information Technology **Z**, Euclidian Geometry **Z** and Microsoft Office Access **Z** 

2012 **Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Engineering**, *Universidad Madero*, México. Fundamentals of Automation **?**, Industrial Electronics **?**, Research Projects **?**, Metrology **?**, Physics **?**, Computer Integrating Manufacturing, and Power Electronics

2007 – 2012 **Teaching Associate in Electronic Engineering**, Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla, México.

Stochastic Processes  ${\bf Z}'$ , Digital Signal Processing  ${\bf Z}'$  and Analog Filters.

08/2006 - 06/2007Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Engineering, Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco, México.

> (January-June 2007.) Electronics I, Numerical Methods, and Electricity and Magnetism. (August-December 2006) Electricity and Magnetism, and Electricity and Industrial Electronics

#### Technical Skills

GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. TensorFlow and PyTorch)[2017-present].

Programming

Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015present], and learning continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

#### Awards and Honours

11/01/2017 My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗷 🖺 🛗

16-18/06/2016 I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh.

20-24/07/2015 My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). ✓ 🛗

11/2014-11/2018 Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology.

25-27/05/2013 Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo.

09/2004-09/2006 M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology.

#### Extra Activities

04-2019 - present Outreach activities and scientific engagement, King's College London, UK.

(02-2020 – 06-2020) Alexandra Lautarescu and I are organising the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital

(20-08-2019) In 2Science UK: sharing my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become

(09-2019) New Scientist Live: showcasing software segmentation that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI.

2013 – present

Founder of LibrE Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children, GitHub: , Website: . (2019–present) Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) GitHub: 🖶 Slides: 🔁

2017 - 2018 Developer of Machine Learning for Mexico, GitHub: 5, Website: 2.

08/2014 - 06/2018 Outreach activities and scientific engagement, University of Birmingham, UK. (05-2018) Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video:  $\stackrel{\text{\tiny th}}{\text{\tiny th}}$  and GitHub:  $\stackrel{\text{\tiny th}}{\text{\tiny th}}$ (2015–2018) Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🖾, (2016) 🖾, and (2018) 🖾. GitHub: 🐱. (2014–2018) Presenting Demos of Human-Robot Interaction at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: 5.

(2017–2018) Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: 👼, Website: 🗹.